all right hello and welcome everyone
it's November 21st 2023 we're here in
active live stream number
56.2 discussing a quartet of papers with
Alex aoria this is the third discussion
we've had we had a DOT zero giving some
background and context we hello welcome
everyone it's November 2th 20 that
Alexander you're inactive live
stream empirical demonstration of the
feedback delay of live streaming so
let's just jump in perhaps blue if you
have any initial kind of remarks or
questions then to Alex and also if
anyone's watching live they can of
course write a question and I'll check
it out so go for it blue and we'll just
jump
in so for me today I think I am really
excited to get into um the cognitive
model so like the last paper was my
favorite and it was um I think maybe
like the most zoomed out so I'm really
kind of looking forward in to getting
into that and then um maybe exploring
what that would look like um in a
non-human system so that's I mean I kind
of always want to go there but I'm still
I still want to go
there cool what figure should we jump to
or or what part of the paper should we
jump to
Alex um I mean whichever one caught I
think yours in Blue's interest I guess
we could go to the architecture one oh I
do want to if you don't mind a tiny
Shameless plug that I just want to take
the moment right now I'm gonna post this
link in the chat because it relates to
our conversation we had in point one um
so this is a paper that just came out
the end of last week um I just want to
add that as context ization especially
blue you might find it interesting
because uh this was work I've worked on
I think I even alluded to it over like
the last seven months um this is why I
was talking about inactive and embodied
cognition uh and uh there's a lot more
so now now it's out there I don't have
to pretend like oh it's a secret project
um that was it so that's my only
Shameless plug let's go back I just I
thought I should start with this so the
the um the not to steal the Thunders of
56.1 were this paper that came out in
the time between yeah it literally came
out last end of last week yeah wow so I
mean maybe just while we're here like
could you just you don't have to review
it I've already had so you already have
so many papers but it might be worth
yeah like could you just give us like
the ele elevator pitch about this paper
and um like maybe your favorite figure
because I mean we were really excited
your comments last week okay so scroll
up Daniel uh it's it's actually early
there's there's cool stuff but go to the
yeah it's a very long paper yeah that
picture it has it also has an appendix
or a supplement but so it was a longer
original paper too uh just that way
again I don't steal the Thunder of this
particular podcast because our Focus was
different um now the the general idea is
uh my my thesis are Carl and my cist
thesis is about moral computation which
is a phrase that Jeffrey Hinton
introduced uh very briefly like in about
like two sentences or a small paragraph
in his paper in December uh and I have
written at length about it in a couple
of my own papers end of December of last
year in January and February um so this
is sort of like uh the big uh Deep dive
into what does it mean to make a
computer that is not Immortal which is
what we have in computer science today
uh the computer is inextricably bound or
rather the software is inextricably
bound to the hardware uh sorry not bound
to the hardware I'm just making a
mistake there so for example we can copy
our software or machine intelligence
program across any amount of computers
and it doesn't really matter um and uh
it's also extremely inefficient and then
the opposite side of that is Mortal
computation which is essentially drawing
inspiration from life itself uh for
example uh when any one of us dies a
human dies uh your computations your
memories your quirks the things that
define who you are are essentially gone
right because it's Unique to you and
that is because you're an embodied in
active agent um and so what's kind of
nice about this diagram is it's it's a
really colorful pretty diagram but it's
in it sort of synthesizes two out of the
three perspectives in this paper so uh
Carl and I investigated
biophysics uh which is sort of like the
intersection of physics physiology
biology chemistry and the ideas that
have echoed over I mean essentially the
last century and that's the top half the
bottom half is a classical and very
interesting domain called cybernetics
which is like the intersection of uh
computer science control theory also
physics and a bunch of other domains and
information Theory and it also has
similar ideas and everything centers
around this idea of
homeostasis and all the millions of uh
variations and higher order uh you know
uh Concepts that build on that in the
ideas that uh our intelligence and uh
essentially is driven by our our per
desire to persist and to survive in an
environment and so this actually takes
my comments from the last point1 podcast
with you guys uh to its natural
conclusion which is I don't just believe
you need a body you need an environment
you need essentially a drive to persist
and to fight uh thermodynamic disolution
or dissipation into the environment or
disintegration is a better word um so we
are essentially a in the biological
second law of Thermodynamics which is
why it's also about free energy uh and
so then uh we and then there's another
but it's also that it's a later diagram
cognitive science and uh Carl and I uh
propose 5e cognitive theory which is
just taking the classical 4E Theory um I
don't remember if I said this too last
time but embedded uh extended uh
inactive and uh you know the and uh yeah
embedded oh embodied foure the
traditional four e we added something
called Elementary cognition which I did
say to you guys basil cognition last
time so this kind of like ties these
three areas together as well as the
philosophy of life and death and ex
existentialism and kind of combines them
together into a unified framework and
then uh we we dive into marot blankets I
I I think they're a beautiful and
elegant formal ISM for tying these ideas
together and getting us a step towards
uh you know the Mortal computation
mortal computer design and then we we we
talk about the free energy principle
underpinnings that essentially the the
Mortal uh computer and bodies and we
review uh a couple of existing mortal
computers which do exist so organoids or
micro physiological intelligence is a
beautiful example of this uh even uh we
talk about fungal computers also Michael
Levens work on xenobots so we have like
a nice little table and then there's an
appendix with a little bit of expansion
on that also we have to give credit to
uh Ashby uh who's a really well-known
and or uh very important cybernetical
scientist cyber cybernetic
cybernetician um and his homeostat which
is also an example of an insilico model
computer so long story short uh
we if we want One path to artificial
general intelligence is not going to be
the way we have it now uh it's not
through just bigger and bigger
Transformers which are extremely energy
efficient they're labeled in the domain
of AI itself red AI if we want green AI
we want Edge Computing we want neuro
robots uh that are also able to do
humanlike actions and enact in humanlike
Behavior Uh because we think for example
the human model or even animal models
right are a good template for how we can
interact and engage in our environment
um then the idea is that we need to
transition to this idea of mortal
computation and leave behind my last
Point here uh the tool oriented view of
artificial general intelligence because
the way we treat AGI today and we say
this towards the end of the paper um
that while it's very important important
and very helpful for Humanity uh to
build artificial intelligence systems
that are very very narrow and very tool
Centric they are more to support
something for a particular task if we
want to build general intelligence uh
then uh Carl and I put forth the moral
computation thesis as one possible
pathway uh to go into the future so this
is sort of also a call for researchers
across all these different domains to
come together ranging from biophysics to
biology to computer science and machine
learning uh to computational
Neuroscience cognitive science it's
pretty much and cybernetics of course
all of them kind of converging to
perhaps build uh a different Pathway to
what we call the Mortal computer and so
I think that wasn't quite a good
elevator pitch that was a little bit
longer but I'm G to stop there because I
think then you can just read the paper
it's it's it's fun
well it's a tall elevator there's a lot
of floors in the
bunker um I think there's a
perfect articulation there 56.2 let's
focus on living functioning cognitive
Frameworks but it's really cool that
you're going into the life and death
elements that way
so I do think that the paper that blue
wants to talk about there's a compliment
to to it because we do mention very
briefly in this paper cognitive
architectures like the common and also
the common model of cognition blueprint
that we also talked about in01 which is
the center basis for the paper that uh
blue was going to ask some questions
about I think uh it's mentioned here
briefly and that we also talked about as
that being uh a potential maybe we don't
say it this way I said it in
conversation to someone but a a a CO an
inductive bias which you did right you
wrot basis I also talk about it as like
the idea of cognitive architecture and
modules of Mind serve sort of like as a
prior and that is uh produced by
Evolution and uh we also talk in the
paper too the moral Computing paper
evolution is important natural selection
is an important ingredient uh and if we
don't use that uh then we have to design
the results of evolution so I think the
common model of cognition which can help
segue into the paper now um is a
beautiful bias it is one of our Best
Bets for how do we emulate the modules
of mind and how things interact um and
this would get at the the neural
computation component of a mortal
computer obviously it does not say
anything about the body about the niche
about other agents but you know you can
imagine it is a little block that would
go into this framework and that would be
one step towards a mortal computer
so so can I just temporarily derail I
just have to ask a followup question I
have to ask my fault for derailing at
the beginning I um so just in terms when
you're when you're talking about Mortal
Computing I mean I just couldn't help
but go to Quantum Computing where the
computation itself is so heavily
dependent on the substrate and the
modality of the hardware right like the
the computation the hardware and the
computation are like really inextricably
linked there um and and in the same way
that like you know I can write a paper
you can write a paper all of these
things will Outlast us like so some of
our computations Will Survive Beyond
like the point where we're biologically
dead right so in a quantum computer
similarly all of those computations can
then be taken and translated and put
into Python and all all of the things
right um but I just wonder to what um
extent and like I know I kind of know
where quantum computers and artificial
intelligence like meet you know like
everything's got to go into the Cubo and
then the answer comes out and so then we
take the answer and put it back into
Python and do regular AI things with it
or in some language right not always
python but sometimes right so where do
you think can a quantum computer or can
we ever get Quantum computation or what
is the role of quantum computation how
can that intermingle with artificial
intelligence and then become a mortal
computer or is that just like too
farfetched we're not going to think
about
that well so the paper doesn't go into
that specifically however we touch on a
little bit because uh a little bit of
the paper and we we cite it plenty uh
Carl's work with Chris fields which I
know he's been on you guys have been
doing a series with him on Quantum
Computing Quantum information Theory um
he had a paper neuromorphic Computing
induces the free energy principle or
some version of that title I read that
many times as well and in there I think
is the way that Quantum Computing or
Quantum information Theory would
interact with the Mortal computer and so
I don't see I see it as another
perspective there could have been a
fourth perspective in this already long
paper um and I did originally have some
ambition to write something about that
and we distilled it to just the concept
that Chris Fields introduces which was
the interface so I think the quantum
information theoretic interpretation of
the brain and the body especially like
as presented in that paper and related
work could be a better way to deal with
the Markoff blanket formalism that uh
Carl and I uh constructed in this paper
this paper uh which is largely grounded
by also my educational back ground too
because I only have uh you know some
moderate knowledge in you know quantum
mechanics uh and it was a while since I
studied that but um in there we are
treating the paper is like a classical
interpretation or you could say almost
the Newtonian interpretation of the free
energy principle and uh and Carl and I
discussed this many times as we were
working on this paper um that that has a
limitation it's not necessarily that you
can't build them more I think this paper
gives you all the the foundation you
need to literally build a mortal
computer get started it's a like a
theoretical mathematical
conceptualization however um there are
some weird things about the
thermodynamic energy exchange between
the internal states of your agent your
entity and the environment and
originally I had a different diagram of
the Markov blanket so that there is
later in the paper you'll see it I
really like that diagram because it
really made yeah you probably saw it it
was there towards the end it looked like
a spider almost um yeah that so this
originally had a different version where
I had these uh extra States uh because I
like to take old Concepts and extend
them myself and I had these
thermodynamic States in there and I had
them tried and I had probabilistic arcs
that wir them all these arcs are
designed carefully to make sure that it
aderes to the mark of blanket principles
of like you know the dependency
relationships between children and
parents and the children of children or
the children of parents um and how they
relate together so I had embedded extra
States and Carl said that I should
remove those because it's uh it violates
the classical interpretation of the free
energy principle and long story short is
that you have this energy Exchange in
the diagram and you can represent that
is dissipation but it's not a state that
the agent would have like access to in
the marov blanket so now back to the
Chris Fields interpretation if you go to
the interface uh I think he calls it
like a Quantum interface he had a or um
he had a name for it it has like this
really fancy symbol in the in the paper
um if you use that you get access it's
not like you have access to manipulate
it but you can sort of perceive it from
the perspective of the agent you see the
sensory and the action state so so the
the partitions of that field um and I'm
probably B butchering his language
Chris's language but and then you also
have like the thermodynamic exchange
portion or partition of that field uh
and like it's like a the non-manipulable
and manipulable portions of it and so I
think that interpretation could be a
more powerful way to like you said blue
earlier that Quantum information Theory
and Quantum uh sorry quantum information
theoretic and Quantum Computing
interpretations lend themselves to that
natural entanglement that this that this
paper uh takes from so again we surveyed
work all the way back to decart uh in
Emanuel con but you know and tying all
their ideas together because by the way
even though we're putting forth the
phrase mortal computation the Mortal
computation thesis uh and trying to
essentially EST established that as our
foundation for all of science to build
on uh it's kind of been
echoed Brilliant Minds thinkers
theoreticians Engineers have existed
forever so uh it's kind of like a
synthesis and unification of already
wonderful ideas across vast parts of all
the domains um but I think the quantum
information theoretic way could be the
next step the fourth perspective to
Quantum Computing and it could lend
itself to maybe easier impementation
especially if you have access to a
quantum computer obviously this is the
joke we had last time uh when we talked
about Evolution and why I specifically
might not directly work in that although
I have some work in genetic algorithms
and neuro evolutionary with uh Travis
desel who was on here for the ant colony
optimization work that was presented um
it's compute right I don't have access
to the quantum computers of our time or
maybe the simulator and of course the
knowledge to perhaps use that
effectively however I think that someone
who does could perhaps take the
principles that are put forth here take
the Chris Fields uh interface
interpretation and he goes into a lot
more detail like he talks about he had
something called like a
tdnn or something it was like the
quantum neural network and they were
trying to come up with the morphology
but the uh the principles there are
echoed in some sense here too we that
work but um obviously but uh Carl's on
there too but the the the principles of
morphology uh which are like essentially
we originally had another word in the
title called morphic uh because the idea
is that intelligence should ultimately
you can't divorce it from any form of
instantiation you got to choose
something you're GNA be brittle but
you're going to be thermodynamically
efficient and I think if you could
interpret it from that perspective the
quantum information theoretic that might
lend itself to a more powerful
implementation uh the last comment I'll
make and I'm already long-winded on this
so the final point is we do also briefly
mention in the conclusion of this paper
and we haven't even talked about the
papers that uh we wanted to about today
but in the
conclusion uh I also mentioned Quantum
Computing but in a weird way so I hope
it doesn't feel too contradictory to
that I just said that if you take the
quantum information theoretic
interpretation of mortal Computing or
build your own interpretation because we
don't really do it much for you here
except mention the the the interface um
while that could be a powerful and
perhaps the best way who knows to
implement it we also mentioned Quantum
computation as sort of like okay others
have been looking at this in Ai and for
example saying like we can do if we have
a properly developed uh quantum computer
we can do big root Force search right we
can do simulated and kneeling faster
than our minds ever could have conceived
with classic comple that's kind of just
been in what's we can do machine
learning better um and we we sort of
argue a little tiny bit against it uh
not against the interpretation but
rather the the fact that Quantum
Computing plus machine learning is just
another way to do what we currently do
which is narrow AI Brute Force search
better and faster and so that's
essentially it keeps live Immortal
computation right because what are we
going to probably do I I I'm not a not
pretending to be a Seer I'm not
pretending to predict the future there's
no way I can know of all people but um
the way we're going about it is that oh
we're gonna try to put chat GPT or some
Transformer like model in a quantum
computer and yeah it's going to work a
lot faster it might be more efficient
but at the end of the day we're going to
be programming that quantum computer at
a separation level right we're going to
try try to deal with it like we do in a
normal operating system maybe we all
have to learn a little quantum mechanics
to do it um and we write our code and we
write our software and then we just hope
that the quantum computer can execute it
really fast that's not the premise that
I would want a quantum computer to be
used that's still Immortal computation
just done in an accelerated faster way
so we do warn or rather are rather even
just more like slightly common that
while Quantum Computing will be
important and uh we there is uh promise
there to even speed up the computations
we do today it's not necessarily its
current use or the way we sort of
project to use it is not the right path
to AGI either so or biomimic
intelligence which is really what the
paper's trying to say if we want to
build biomimic AGI maybe there's other
types of AGI and I don't mean like
animal because animals are definitely a
part of this paper uh organism anything
that maintains homeostasis to some level
that's what this paper says is the the
pathway to that style of AGI there might
be something else again I don't want to
comment on whether or not uh large
language models and Transformers and
these new architectures there might be
something alien that I can't foresee and
maybe Quantum Computing will make that
uh you know more energy efficient and
some way or faster it's still going to
carry forward though the premise of
tool-based
I and uh you know AI uh in the way that
we do it narrow AI I don't think it's
going to lend itself to the path that we
would really want general intelligence
and general intelligence really is tied
uh at least if we use organisms as our
exemplars tied to the fact that we we
don't have forever right uh that we we
know to some degree whether we're
conscious or unconsciously aware of the
fact that I am at odds with my
environment I'm going to behave in this
way in service of that and of course
Evolution uh encodes some of that
knowledge going into it um so I just
want to comment that I I think that it's
it depends on how you use the quantum
perspective like if you use it from like
the Chris Field's Quantum information
theoretic interpretation of the markup
blanket that might be a really excellent
way for someone to even follow up on
this and add the fourth perspective that
Carl and I kind of just dance around a
little bit or an mation I think there
could be some really fascinating things
here but if you're just using Quantum
Computing uh to accelerate your normal
run current day machine learning the
current approaches that we have uh then
you're just still carrying forward the
banner of immortal computation and again
too I want to make one last comment just
because we talked about it um this paper
says we need Mortal computation and uh
it was weird there isn't uh much more
than Jeff's one mention of it in his
2022 Ford Ford learning paper then my
paper had a little bit longer section
the predictive Ford Ford algorithm and
then I had the spiking version of the
Ford Ford the the pioneered that idea
and we had like an introduction like
about a page about Mortal computation
and then there's this one with Carl
which is you know a really really long
uh doozy of a paper um so aside from
that I've only seen mortal computation
sort of discussed oh I see a little bit
of Mortal Kombat appearing um I see
discussions like brief mentions of
mortal computation but there was
something that Jeff mentioned somewhere
along the line or maybe it was an
interpretation of it I don't also think
mortal computation should completely
replace Immortal computation I think
both have a place in society we just
need to understand that they both do
different things and they both have
different purposes if we want you know
intelligent agents and neuro robots I'm
on the camp you need Mortal computation
to do it right but uh if we want that
type of General Behavior but Immortal
computation is not going to go away it's
just more like we understand it has a
very high thermodynamic cost because we
have to deal with the Von noyman
bottleneck the memory bottleneck we're
not using in memory processing um maybe
a Quantum Computing will speed that up
too and then Immortal computation can
live side by side and we'll have those
as tools
so I also want to make that clear for
anyone that ever watches you know this
recording later uh that the Mortal
computation thesis isn't to say it's the
only way to do computation it's just we
should shake up the roots of computer
science at its foundation and say maybe
there's another way to do it and we
should have both live side by side and
hey this one might lend itself to AGI um
which by the way some people might
disagree with that as well I don't again
I we do offer it very humbly in the
paper as one possible pathway not the
because again I could be completely
wrong there could be a better way to do
this but um
yeah so well that was a really good
answer and you really articulated like
what I was trying to ask about and I
think um it's actually really easy to
get access to a quantum computer but
it's not it's really easy to get access
to the
interface to a quantum computer and I
think that what you what you keyed in on
is like you need the morphology you need
the structure like so in order to play
with a quantum computer and program the
quantum computer to do Mortal
computation you actually have to play
with the substrate itself and not just
have access to the computer through some
interface Network right yep bingo
bingo to kind of bring us towards the
nonhuman cognitive modeling sl4
paper something coming up in that was
all the different ways that we talk
about interface and also the different
ways we represent it like this is really
creative and I've never seen the um
blanket represented this way with a with
a
Zone and which connects nicely to the
the blanket index but whether we're
talking about the kind of strict
analytical Bas graph Markov blanket or
the quantum interface or just an
engineering interface input output or
flow diagram systems Dynamics or the the
kind of perhaps most general or
accounting system of them all like
applied category Theory we're describing
these different facets of the
interface so that's one place to begin
when modeling a non-human or a human
cognitive architecture is its interfaces
it's like if those aren't accounted for
we're either speculating information
that we're measuring or observing or
interacting with this cognitive thing
rather speculating about what we could
do or about what we could
measure or we're missing things that we
actually can intervene with and measure
so maybe how do we go
about before even wondering about which
formalism it's going to be described as
how do we think about the interface of a
cognitive
system that's yeah
well you just brought up a really good
point I just want to point out that you
said uh if we don't design you know the
interface between let's say the internal
states of the agent which just to
connect it to the cognitive modeling
paper you could think of the common
model of cognition as the design of the
internal States right it's the brain
right and uh let's just keep it like the
organization or principles of the brain
because again I think of CMC common
model of cognition as a blueprint and
you know Cog engine which is what that
paper is about is a physical well it is
a computational instantiation of some
pieces of
CMC um and even that is still only a
part of the puzzle so but you could
think of that that's going to be what's
inside the Markoff blanket all right uh
and then of course inside of it could be
more Markoff blankets because we also
talk about markup blankets of markup
blankets of markof blankets and there's
a recursive assembly kind of but uh you
brought up Daniel if you don't
design uh it could also be an engineered
you know uh permeable boundary with
pumps and things that you know for
example remove toxins from the internals
of the agent and brings in nutrients and
energy which we do talk about as well in
the in the Mortal computation paper um
regardless of the formalism you're all
if you don't account for it and you
don't so while Cog engine does not
account for it it's still one of those
like well we're going to just say we're
looking at some very very specific
internal States and we're going to probe
it in a very specific way although we
kind of have an agent because we do use
the gym minig grid so there is a body
but it's like a really really really
simplified body uh you're missing out on
a lot of intelligence and cognition that
the boundary itself will give you so
even in cells right so this is to take
what you said Daniel and you know Jack
uh boost it even higher the boost the
signal uh is that I also believe a lot
of the intelligent computations that we
do can be are offloaded right this is
the embodiment thesis of cognitive
science the the even the permeable cell
boundary right of just single cell
organisms or multicellular organisms uh
it does a lot of beautiful things that
the internal states are not doing like
uh consciously or directly with effort
may actually should be careful with
Consciousness at different levels but um
the that boundary the mark of blanket
offloads some of that compute that the
brain or the internal States need to
worry about um and it can they can sort
of rely on what the boundary does now of
course there's more to that story that
even the Markov blanket doesn't
necessarily need to address it U but
there's the fact that there's also autop
pesis so the ideas that the system
reproduces it's self- reproducing that's
where why there's a lot more it's a
paper that very much is like an iceberg
you can read the beginning and be like
that's a beautiful phrase and then
what's underneath it is this extremely
deep and I don't even think I Carl and I
have properly even captured all the
facets that you could add to this
there's more like we just talked about
the quantum interpretations as well um
so assuming that we have everything
taken care of that things self-heal
self-repair uh the the boundary itself
is in you know constant reconstruction
uh you you have this nice power or nice
advantage that you not only account for
how energy flows in and out of the
system and things that you would
normally not account for in our
traditional agents that we design today
um but you would also have the ability
to offload cognition there's even a
domain we mention it in the paper too
but uh you might have heard of
morphological robotics um and there's
even classical ideas going back to even
I believe even Rodney Brooks mentioned
aspects of this as well in some of his
early work uh if you study the way that
we move our joints and our arms uh you
know there's a lot of uh cognition
offloaded into that act and you can also
get that in terms of Robotics too and
just saying by understanding the you
know kinematics that drive an arm now
the robotic brain if you will the neuro
robot only needs to say I need to move
my hand to this point and then it can
sort of trust its digital nervous system
or rather the actual constructs in the
robotic Hardware to move the rest of the
arm like he doesn't have to think
consciously about moving the elbow just
needs to move the point if you know from
computer Graphics inverse kinematics
right you only need to move the point of
the hand to where you want to go and
then the rest takes care of the mo
motion and it looks you know it doesn't
break the constraints of how like the
bones are structured and the SK little
structure of the Armature of the
character so uh I think you there's even
more to just model not just mod so we do
talk about modeling too because some of
us or a lot of us might not have access
to the hardware as well right I think
it's in the appendix I think it had to
be moved to the supplement of the paper
because it was already very long oh yeah
it is in the supplement but we have this
problem called the body Niche problem uh
and besides the fact it's a nice
sounding philosophical problem there's
this issue that uh robotic Hardware or
even organoid you know constructs or
biological substrates or CH won't be
available to everyone so if we want to
democratize things we're going to
probably need to model these digitally
and so we have this concept called a
digital morphology so maybe we can take
whatever principles of physics and other
aspects of thermodynamics maybe we can
construct bodies that we can simulate
for cheap so people can work on Mortal
computers simulated right uh although
the ultimate would be you just like blue
brought up earlier about the best way to
use a a quantum computer would be to
literally have access to the quantum
computer and then design your internal
States your software that would run run
it uh literally on chip right or on on
quantum computer whatever the right word
for that would be but they're entangled
so you're completely uh you're only
paying the cost the thermodynamic cost
of reading and writing to the memory
right on the chips or right on the
actual platform itself uh rather than
having these separations right even
including like operating systems and the
transfer of memory and a hierarchy and
so having the actual Hardware would be
the best and I think that's where you
know even the work kind of says this is
where the future really lies but
probably along the way we could probably
work with digital morphologies as well
so long answer but just to say that your
point is great and we could boost it
even further by offloading cognition to
the body and I also think because you
said what formalism would you choose and
I don't think any one formalism is you
know like Superior per se they give you
different things I think the mark of
blanket is nice because it connects to
uh beian probability and then you can
kind of at least characterize the
relationships between states um but from
an engineering point of view I don't
think you like directly have to design
the exact markup blanket because now
you're dealing with a graphical model
and what would you what do we usually do
we usually choose discret States and the
world's continuous I thought about this
like I thought okay now that this paper
has come out how do I build my own
mortal computer right just to show how
we could do this uh but you know I think
Michael Levan has a great example uh
with the xenobots like that's one way to
do it although it's very biological
artificial um but I think just designing
boundaries and sort of clearly
explaining or accounting for the
thermodynamic exchange and understanding
like what are the resources that we have
at hand even in a very controlled
environment might be the way to design
the Markov blanket because then you get
for free if you have like and I think we
talked last time about like a quadr ped
orur a robot like spot or something and
you know have it outside right if you
already choose your body and you put it
in an environment you've already now
dealt with the boundary and the niche
you just need to understand the
properties of that which is where we can
Leverage The the wonderful knowledge
across domains like physics and biology
and chemistry understand the properties
of that body right understand the
properties of that Niche and then all we
have to work on is the internal State
Design
and how does that interact with
maintaining persistence right for
example battery level power level that's
a homeostatic variable or a metabolic
variable there you go now you can build
your agent about keeping that variable
uh in within a certain range right
because homeostasis is about a set point
so may have a Target or actually the we
changed the word to something more
powerful homeorhesis which is
homeostasis over time right because set
points might change like in flux to the
environment um so that's that's a kind
of a cool concept as well there's like a
word for everything I learned when
writing this paper so many Concepts
already exist all we have to do is just
stitch them together and this is one way
to stitch them together into a nice
little framework um so did that make
sense yeah I'll I'll make a note and
then blue I'll be curious to see what
you think about this I think with what
you've just described you you've almost
given some of the most specific ways to
think about what is off loadable we've
talked about extended cognition and
about having passive artifacts in the
niche like paper and pen and then having
active artifacts in the niche like
autonomous agents or whether they're
material or or just
digitalized so it's interesting that by
putting certain computation on the
boundary or on the interface broadly
conceived with both a material
thermodynamic and a informational
semantic component then it's like yeah
the nucleus doesn't decide about the
cell morphology and so it's like how
many layers can you put in
between in between so that the
computation goes out to the interfaces
everywhere's an interface from somewhere
and that's where the work is really done
and then there's just so many other
great points but what do you think about
this kind of conclusion to
2023 live streams after long arcs with
thinking about embod cognition and
cognitive
architectures um so wow what is off
loadable uh I I have a lot to say about
that um uh so like in terms of what the
body does um and let me know if my
internet cuts out and I'll shut my video
off um but in terms of what the body
does like it's like you think about
things that are automatic right like the
heartbeat and the breath um and and
stuff that like we just ignore and like
I mean if you really you could do biof
feedback and slow your heart heart rate
and like breathing you can definitely
control I mean it's very obvious that
you can control it um but but like I
wonder about these things like what is
offloaded to the body that we're
ignoring right like if you offload too
much you know like we have like gut
reactions to
like like you know these like Sensations
and there's like a lot of computation
happening within our own morphological
structure that maybe we're not conscious
of like so a lot of is unconscious but
then like are we overlooking stuff that
we should then be paying attention to
like I like I wonder what is the price
of of
offloading that's a great
question um I mean I don't know to be
fair I can't say I know the exact sweet
spot because that would also mean that I
have uh the exact instantiation of the
Mortal computer that I wish to build
right um you know the answer is we need
to study that uh that's the short answer
the slightly longer
answer how do I say this without letting
myself
ramble well so maybe there is a point
where we cross where we had let's say
humans animals even any any entity has
failed to find The Sweet Spot like you
just said blue uh even we
humans when we do something you know we
have a gut reaction and we might tend to
listen to that gut reaction rather than
doing some other type of processing like
thinking critically or logically and
counteracting it we also have emotions
which I think is very important which we
don't really quite have that uh in
today's AI but uh we do kind of have a
little bit of some good work has been
done in cognitive science and cognitive
architectures
but I think that we might have already
crossed the sweet spot because some of
us listen more to our guts and our
emotions than logical logic or reasoning
or you know planning things out more
carefully or listing pros and cons some
of us might not listen enough to our gut
feelings and we listen too much so I
think the diversity uh in even within
any entity such as a human is vast and
so maybe someone has the optimal sweet
spot I don't know who does it varies but
it doesn't matter so it's kind of
interesting we it's it's an interesting
question to quantify and worth looking
at but at the same time in designing a
mortal computer let's say I failed to
design the one that has the right
balance let's say I designed a computer
that mortal computer that leaned more
heavily towards gut reactions uh than
not well I would still be thrilled that
we built such a computer because while
it would be great to find and
characterize these set points or sorry
these boundaries and
regions um we would still have the
premise that look life is built on these
hierarchical or rather layers of
complexity so homeostasis homeo sorry
homeorhesis and homeostasis which sit at
sort of the bottom of what we talk about
in the paper um and then underneath that
are like got to be careful a little bit
but they're like metabolic pathways or
what we or Carl and I call Essential
Primitives or variables which are kind
of like the materials and the the very
based constructs that maybe we you know
manipulate to survive with but above
that are things like
allostasis and complex processing and of
course we put at the top of our
hierarchy autop pesis but technically uh
the idea is that everything would be
self-repairing and healing but if we put
the growth and dynamic change aside for
just a minute our allostasis can be argu
and it has been argue to be all kinds of
things it can be uh oh we have little
neural circuits that try to uh predict
when homeostatic processes are going to
need resources and so this is where you
can see it in animals and uh insects and
other types of uh creatures that oh I
know that uh the seasons are going to
change like Birds they fly to another
and they so they have these kind of
instincts built in or they have some
sensors in circuit processing to say I
should probably go somewhere else where
I'm not going to Die For the Win turn so
then they flock away right or they fly
away so there's already some higher
level Behavior built on there the reason
I bring up that just to tie it back to
that balance point that you bring blue
is that we would have the opportunity to
design those neural processes that could
override for example your gut reaction
or your more primitive instincts and so
this is what's kind of nice about the
Mortal computer is we would want that
ability to do planning to do higher
level thinking and this is again what
connects nicely to the cognitive
architecture right if we have a more
developed let's say brain region area
right we have different types of memory
like procedural declarative memory um
now we're able to start to think at a
higher level that's not just purely
driven by our instincts and so the 5D
cognitive theory uh in the paper
Elementary cognition I don't think is
the only thing you need that would be
like I only rely on my gut instincts I
am primitive in the sense Primal I only
want to live and I will do whatever it
takes to live but for example if you
live in a society of mortal computers
which is one way you could think of
humans I'm not going to start calling my
friends Mortal computers but we live in
a in a relationship we have a we are
complex system and ourselves well now
we're not just only thinking about uh
exactly like I I don't want to die right
now right because if that's how we live
then you know we go back to uh kill or
be killed law of the Jungle right we are
just sort of fighting amongst each other
so I think while it's hard to answer
what's The Sweet Spot or the balance
point I would still think having a
mortal computer that even has the
ability to engender those Primal gut
instincts would be very powerful and
then we could work on thinking well what
are the right neural processes to
counteract that right to add the
critical logical thinking what
constructs would have Evolution evolved
to allow us to counteract that um does
that make sense because I think like
it's almost like it's a good question to
ask but I don't think it's uh it's more
like it would be OD it would be profound
if we had something that leaned a little
too heavily on its gut instinct and we
say okay but now we have these
allostatic processes we're just missing
more of that higher level be Behavior to
counteract that uh because we humans are
able to for example ignore even
sometimes our Primal needs our desire
not maybe completely desire to persist
because some of that's very deep low
level um but like we even have the act
of like heroism right you know like I'm
gonna go save someone that I care about
and that will end your persistence you
will thermodynamically disintegrate when
you know I go into the fire right so we
have these higher level cognitive
processes we're going to need to design
those too or let some evolutionary
process let those emerge so um I would
still we just don't have the low level
either and we we might not have the full
picture of the higher level but right
now a lot of artificial intelligence
doesn't even have that that Primal
persistence right so I I think I would
be thrilled to have that problem and say
oh blue it's a little too survival
oriented maybe we could try to uh
introduce the right mechanisms to
counterbalance that that's another
thought so I just am rereading a book by
um the theoretical physicist Fred Allen
wolf and he talks about um like
literally in terms of quantum
entanglement he talks about the
entanglement of thought and emotion
which I think like thinking about
Quantum Computing and quantum
entanglement like the entanglement
between thought and emotion is just like
a really
interesting concept to me or just an
interesting way to think about like who
wins or like can you have one without
the other or one always knows what the
other one is doing
or
yeah and the problem we have in I agree
we have that entanglement and is
fascinating the problem in uh artificial
systems or technological artifacts which
by the way another theme of this paper
and we sort to wrap it up is it's like a
path to it's going to sound a little odd
artificial sentience and then that also
opens up the whole moral uh issues and
ethical dilemmas but um but to even get
there I would argue we're missing the
half of your entanglement right we're
missing more the emotional side which I
think also stems from you know even the
lower level processes that kind of give
rise to the emotional states and because
you know there's there's a lot of
physiology and a lot of physiological
connections between like the chemicals
and things in our body that also help
drive those emotions and I think we need
them and I think artifi technological
artifacts are missing at least I'm not
going to say if we've tackled
sufficiently the higher level cognitive
uh Behavior because you know there's
still the work being done in cognitive
architectures and cognitive modeling um
although I also think that we're because
we're missing half which is the
emotional side of things and the
biophysical drives and manipulations
we're missing that entanglement so the
design of our intelligence system is
sort of like detached we're still in
many ways in Ai and we also mention this
in that paper uh you might have heard of
brain inovat right which is the idea of
what you can think of it intuitively
it's an old cognitive it no one really
ever said it it's more of like a
criticism of old cognitive science which
is to say that neural processing our
mental
representations our decisions and that
we make and our plans that we make and
our complex logical order processing are
completely divorced of the body right
it's the
extreme uh it's essentially mortal
Immortal computation which is kind of
another fun thing we pointed out um but
in the cognitive sciences and philos
philosophy of Mind realm and because
we've been designing things from that
perspective for so long uh we're missing
that entanglement and I think there's
some of the roadblocks we will face in
the future some of the things we can't
necessarily build maybe the holy Grails
that still remain like you know higher
order logical reasoning and uh complex
planning that you know Transformers and
the big neural models can't really quite
do today despite claims that are being
made uh from the public relations of
different companies um I think that
we're missing that other piece of the
equation that could have helped inform
and make those processes that we design
better but we're also missing that
relationship so that entanglement blue
is inherently not there uh which is
there in for example human entities and
animals and or living beings right we
have that interplay and then we have the
ability to decide if we want to override
it but technological artifacts don't
have that there's nothing override right
so um at least I'm going to make that
claim I'm sure that there's probably
there is this world called Effective
computing um but I'm not 100% clear if
whether or not that has all the
ingredients that I would say need to be
in place to build that 50% of the
entanglement of emotion to higher level
cognition and reasoning and
non-emotional reasoning um so and we
need that so i' would love to have that
and then we could then quantify that
entanglement right and talk about the
relationship or proportion of emotional
processing or even low-level biological
processing to higher level or cognitive
processing and planning and decision
making I don't know if blue heard that
but I see her thing green
so okay
yeah
wow I I brought up an image this is a
figure 1.2 from the textbook with the
high road and the low road so the low
road how it's constructed and that's
basian but we could consider other ways
that things are actually built like JF
clout you're working on the symbolic
active inference so programs from the
bottom up or there could be different
heterogenous elements we talked about
Quantum and neuromorphic so
as many material substrates as there are
material substrates to be inclusive of
what ecosystems actually consist of and
then first
principles thinking first principles
approaches including the free energy
principle or unified through
consideration with the free energy
principle all of these terms that
include complex systems phenomena
self-organization autop is like you
mentioned
and
how the current narrow or whatever it is
computer science that we continue to
ride inertia and acceleration on from
the kind of Von noyman architecture um
and scaling in in materials with a lot
of
costs like that is almost missing these
two compliments one of them is the top-
down organizing principle though there
are organizational principles within
computer science of course it's a formal
field but unified principle and then
almost like in a in a very interesting
relation that that I hope people can
explore later is this other
complimentary
relationship between I mean to put it
coarsely like the heart and the brain
and the integration with the hands and
about pragmatic value and the a
effective value and blue you ask like
what if we're what if we're like least
aware of what we offloaded it's like
that's we're we're only aware of what we
not
offloaded so every every if we just take
a a mental survey of what we know that's
the remainder of what we don't
know and that's a very different very
integrated
compressible perspective that then can
unroll a lot of different ways
that isn't just like we have to do what
we're doing now but just
more well and just a quick Point there's
also this beautiful concept called and
it's being embraced in cognitive science
more recently because it was even the
theme of cogi I believe last year
cognitive diversity you know and so uh
and that's the beautiful part of
embodiment the embodiment thesis in
cognitive science which is it can give
you an explanation
of all the different ways in which we
might have something more offloaded than
you know not uh into the different
varying degrees and so even maybe the
question sometimes isn't what's optimal
but rather can we capture the wide array
of different amounts of cognitive
offloading because if you change the
body you change the cognition and that's
like the embodiment thesis in its
natural and this paper Echoes that
extreme kind of of you a bit that if you
change the body you're going to change
the thinking and fundamentally and you
we know this even even internally within
the same body if you are feeling sick if
you are feeling uh hungry or you have
these you're even if you you can fight
these things with a top- down approach
to some degree but uh it will affect for
example your focus if you're sick it's
harder sometimes to write a paper you
have something called brain fog right
and so that's where the body is so
intimately involved uh in our biophysics
and our physiology so intimately
involved in our everyday
processing that uh and different people
are affected to different degrees I mean
I'm sure there's someone out there who
like no I'm uh maybe they had for
example h a really bad cold and they're
like no I was able to get the same
amount of work done as always right I
mean and that would also show you that
it's going to be vastly different even
within the same type of entity and so um
that that's something cognitive
diversity I think gets captured by this
type of thinking and it could be really
interesting you know from using the
premise of a mortal computer to sort of
construct systems that are like that and
by the way the Mortal computer rests on
that nice diagram that you have there
you know with active inference and the
free energy it sort of tries to hit most
of those main points and sort of like
agglomerate them into well we even
propose a definition right right I mean
is it a complete definition I'm sure
there's extensions uh there's probably
corollaries to add to the Mortal
computation thesis um but I just wanted
to throw that point in there because I
think that that's where it's that that
how much we offload will also change
even if it's like maybe not optimal but
you know that would be more dictated by
an evolutionary process um but you have
different entities and different
organisms that offload to different
degrees and depending on your body and
what affordances it gives you what what
abilities it offers you to interact with
affordances in the environment and tools
and things like that um if I had eight
legs I'm going to be able to do
drastically different things than you
know with my bipedal body right now and
morphological robotics usually explores
some of that um what can different
bodies beyond the humanoid style uh
provideing for example quadruped robots
which they take you know another thing
in nature like oh let's say animals like
dogs and cats but they're wonderful for
like search and rescue right whereas a
bipedal system might struggle to get
into certain spots but if we had a qu
and there we've changed the body and
hence we've changed the cognition in the
mental neural
processing yeah a lot lot just even from
the outside of robot otics I hear about
cognitive robotics so the adjective is
saying well we're pulling back to
consider cognitive architectures and
then there's another layer which is like
well how does it get there what's the
developmental trajectory and then what
is the Ecology of similar or different
minds and and bodies and then what's the
evolutionary process you can keep the um
like you you you again in in in um kind
of Distinction describe the immortal
it's designed as if Immortal but of
course in
reality the Linux operating system or
any given language model is Mortal you
just unplug it because its energy
resources aren't accounted for so it's
kept in this suspended bar life state
where it's at the behest of something
else and so then that like
unsustainability propagates through a
system causing
externalities so ensuring that the
externalities can be under
understood where they
are it leads so we expect to scalable
interpretable
systems that don't just hide the
semantic ambiguity and the um
material components they're so
abstractly
considered and it's so un integratable
with emotive
components that it feels like a dead
endend
so I hate to keep talking about Mortal
computation but we're doing
it well it is your it's your guys
podcast I'm happy to lab about anything
I just want to make sure that if you
wanted to talk about those Pap by the
way we did talk about those papers last
time too and they're integrated right
maybe we can relate some of them like I
keep bringing the Cog engine paper not
because it of itself is Mortal but uh I
argue that it is a piece of that puzzle
like if I were to go yeah that
architecture there that's not a mortal
computer however it is a cognitive
architecture and I think it plays a role
in the design of systems right for
example maybe blue it helps it would
help us for example to design higher
level processing to counteract some of
the lower level emotive uh you know
decisions that an agent would want to
make so I just want to make a mention
I'm fine with talking about whatever I'm
the one that shamelessly plugged I just
actually wanted to plug it and then you
know we could go from there if you but
the there they're they're intertwined
right it it's not like my thinking is oh
when I work on Cog engine I turn off the
Mortal computer it's like no they're all
they're all swirling around it's all
part of the same thought so if you want
to keep talking about it be my guest I'm
your guest so I ju I just have a
question about like when we talk about
scalability and interpretability um I I
wonder how much interpretability is due
to the fact that you know we're missing
that
emotive setup right like so if we have
some kind of interplay between like
persistence emotion thought like if
there's some kind of you know struggle
like who's winning the the war when we
make a decision when we choose to act um
are we going to lose interpretability
when we start to design mortal
computation like or is there a way that
we can keep interpretability I mean I
guess we do all the programming so you
know you keep there is is it going to
end up being more black box if we have
like I mean a human is way like I don't
know what's like I just compute you know
I don't know what's going on I mean I
could try to check in and like where's
this coming from is this my logical
brain or is this from my heart or is it
just like you know a a motor like
kinesthetic memory or or that's driving
me to act in in a certain way like I can
try to dissect it but even it's hard to
know my own like computational process
so when we're looking at like designing
an artificial system are we going to
lose that interpretability in in the
design is that like built
in well fascinating uh point or
fascinating
premise I think it depends not to bust
out the famous it depends answer and any
of my students listening will be like
well there he goes under the shield of
it depends but it really does and I
think it depends on what
interpretability you're looking for and
I'm also going to mix and it is
different to some degree
explainability and I'm G to bring in
that word here because there there's
those that work in like interpretable AI
versus explainable Ai and they can get
pretty mad if you like say oh it's the
same thing and it's not quite um so in
designing let's say a mortal computer
let's even say like a so in the paper we
also uh have sort of like Beginnings uh
Because by the way we are encouraging
everyone to contribute we have sort of
like a lowlevel or what we call a
homeotic or homeostatic mortal computer
and then things that have other
processes are allostatic and things that
are at the top level the complex
computer would be autoptic and that
would be like the ideal that would be
like oh well there we have a human right
we have an animal we have at least a
sentient organoid
um yeah if you're looking for Daniel
it's like after it's in section five uh
under the definition but if you wanted
to see that little it's like it's sort
of a taxonomy uh and then we use it to
evaluate modern day mortal computers no
scroll it's not a picture no no no it's
a under the definition it's it's a
bullet point scroll down you were CL
it's it's weird to find it all right
yeah go down that's the definition and
then you scroll down right there so
there yeah we you had it you had it
right there uh scroll up a little more
no a little
more scroll a little more there
homeostatic allostatic autopedic so we
sort of give a little bit of a
characterization of like Mortal
computers of varying complexity um so
I'm referring to this just in answering
Blue's question if I designed the
ideal MC mortal computer uh autoptic
right so it has all the ingredients we
want and you're saying is it
interpretable do we lose some
interpretting I would argue not
completely you will from a so the the
parts of interpretability you preserve
and I think it's even better in some
ways than your run-of-the-mill
Transformers and large neural models
that are in operation
today is when for example chat GPT or
GPT 5 or stable diffusion does something
really interesting like oh it can do
this Downstream task that I never
expected to do uh like zero shot
learning which you know arguably is very
interesting and promising that these
models can do some elements of this uh
type of
adaptation we can't answer why that
happens the best answer we have is well
it's because we keep throwing more and
more parameters at these models more
neurons more synapses that connect them
and so if I toss more Legos at this
it'll just emergent you know through
emergence
create complex behavior and we get these
nice little properties and it's
interesting because that does relate to
complex system complex adaptive systems
theory like John Holland's work in the
90s and the Santa Fe Institute um and
other other people that have worked on
dynamical systems and uh complexity
Theory and how you get complex
structures that emerge from these very
simple structures and self-organization
was actually on Daniel's uh hierarchy it
was like a one piece of an organizing
principle so that part is like the part
where it might be hard to completely
interpret uh why does this Behavior
emerge because it is this complex
multi-level interaction of parts and you
could at least say it comes from like
and we do talk about it too in the paper
uh because we do talk about self
organization is you can't without if
you're going to talk about any living
system you have to go into
self-organization uh
upward causation and downward causation
so upward causation is like the little
Parts give rise to complex emergent
Parts um and then their relationships to
each other and then the top down
causation is you have these higher level
parts that have now laws and physical
relationships and implicit relationships
with each other that exert like a
modulation modulatory effect on the
lower level parts and so that's why you
have top down bottom up like caus arrows
of causation and interaction and
constraint so to give rise to a complex
system um and so you can point to those
pieces and say well that's the reason
why certain behaviors probably emerged
um but then you get into nonlinear
systems and it's very very hard to even
you know well mathematically analyze
them um let alone you know come up with
intuitive qualitative pictures of what's
going on but the part that you also get
in designing a mortal computer and like
the Cog engine architecture that Daniel
has here on the slide is you get
interpretability in terms at least the
structure and some roles especially if
we're talking about like the internal
States like the reason I like the common
model of cognition and there's other you
know theories and blueprints out there
it's not to say it's the only one um but
the reason I really like it is it sort
of cuts up or cleaves the mind up into
these G eneral Blobs of
responsibilities and has some
relationships it doesn't commit you to
any implementation as we talked about uh
at Point the podcast point. one but it
sort of tells you like oh procedural
memory it's going to be doing this very
specific thing right it's going to learn
how to memorize sequences of actions
kind of like a reactive physiological
physical reactive components and you
know the way I interpret it was the
transition Dynamics model of active
inference or let me build a predictive
coding little structure that tries to
guess latent States but then you have
like declarative memory and it stores
the facts of the world things that you
know I I bind the name of a person to
their face and you know I'm storing
these little bits of knowledge into my
representations and declared in memory
so you get the interpretability at least
at the level of I know what these
modules are doing I probably could
investigate and probe in even a
computational fashion the content of
memory uh cognitive architectures in
general and so that's the part that I
like they bring at least a level of
interpretability because you have this
organizational principles you have
responsibilities for different modules
and even classical cognitive
architectures have things like
production systems and you can encode
knowledge into them uh there's uh good
work on like you know if then statements
and you can kind of break up knowledge
into at least bits and pieces of logic
and we can very easily inspect that
right uh and so the uh while that might
not be computational in the most
efficient way uh we could probably do
mappings between the neural
representation since they're essentially
mimicking what like actar and sore and
very classic prominent cognitive
architectures are trying to do to these
production systems there's been good
work even from yashua's group uh he had
a paper uh neural production systems
which I kind of like that idea about how
do we emul that piece of cogn cognitive
architectures with you know just neural
networks um and so we can we can take
advantage of that mapping and we could
probably get some decoding going on and
interpret some pieces of our agent
system mortal computer um and also by
the way the very design of the Mortal
computer you actually would have a clear
picture of like well these are the
essential variables or the metabolic
pathways here are the homeostatic
process CES these are the things I
defined that Define the life of this
system or otherwise it will die right
and then the allostatic processes live
above that and so that's what that like
cool picture that I really like in the
middle of the paper the biophysics shows
you like the hierarchy of different
types of processing that would happen
from biology and then the cybernetics
tells you what is it going to do from
like an analysis point of view it's you
know trying to uh you know find stable
state it wants to be ultra stable to use
ashbs and the cyberneticists old terms
right and that's you know I'm able to
very quickly uh satisfy my constraints
so I can keep living and not you know
die um and essentially preserve uh or
have enough internal variety to
counterbalance my external variety and
that's the cybernetician uh kind of
framing of what's going on in in in
organizing systems and so you get that
interpretability in terms of the design
you know the parts the mechanisms behind
it but you will lose the piece of like
why did that behavior specifically come
about it's going to be a nonlinear
process so you will lose it and I don't
think you can get all of that back
here's the last point I said at the very
beginning
explainability now this is different
than interpretability and the way I it's
going to be my digested version of
explainability so blue you were saying
to me earlier uh I might be able to
inspect the contents of my mind and come
up with a reasoning for why I did
something and then you mention that well
it could be wrong or you know I might
not completely capture it and I agree
because we do this in all the fields
right like especially anything about the
mind I try to think about the contents
of why I did something or what was going
on in my brain or break down my process
and then try to turn that into a Model A
computational model that then explains
like the actual entity and it might be
wrong it might be biased however there's
something cool about what you doing that
that's the explainable part ybl might
not know the true reason the real reason
of the universe or the biological
reasoning or the thermodynamic cognitive
reasoning of why you did something
specifically however you can provide an
explanation or a rationalization of why
you did it and while it might not be
perfect and we shouldn't you know take
the account as wholesale the exact truth
um you are able to
communicate the basis of your decision
so you are able to use your construct
your biology your neuroprocessor to
formulate and then of course we also
have this thing called communication you
use the other parts of your body to
transmit those sound waves to me and
Daniel across a tool Zoom um and we hear
what you're saying and you say oh I I
when I wanted to solve this problem I
did X Y and Z and what we would find is
then if we did X Y and Z maybe that's
not exactly the true explanation why you
did it but I would be able to solve the
problem now and we teach right we pass
on this knowledge and so the explainable
part might arise I think that might
counterbalance the lack of
interpretability so while we might not
be able to say exactly 100% I still
argue we have more interpretability than
monolith structures like Transformers
today where we just say it
emerged and that's cool right I mean
there is probably analysis I don't want
to like completely dismiss uh
Transformers there probably is
interesting work on maybe identifying
what parts of the network but from the
design principles or the inductive bias
that Evolution gave us I think a
cognitive architecture gives you some
interpretability in a structural way but
then you're going to get a mortal
computer that would probably be able to
explain to you why did it do this
because why the 5 cognition theory that
Carl and I have doesn't it absorbs or
expands for E cognitive theory which
includes embedded and the embedded
cognition is really important because
that's part of that like other diagram I
had where I had the slices of a pie of
cognition in a mortal computer and among
there it's saying I have to interact
with other
well I had other neuro robots but I'm
talking to you blue and that means that
I have to be able to communicate some
approximation of why I did something and
there is an explainable you know there's
explainability and I communicate this
reasoning to you you give me feedback
and you know we we kind of come up with
a solution to the problem or a better
understanding of something and I think
that's where the Mortal computer in its
full Glory would give you right because
it would be able to tell you why it
would interact with you because it also
needs to because you're part of its
Niche you affect its survival so it
can't sort of like uh oh okay I'm just
gonna ignore you because actually it
might be really important you might be
important for it to achieve its goals
which could be to allow it to get more
power if we go back to the Primal
connection there's a lot of jumping
around going on here but you are an
essential part we human humans all of us
are an essential part of what a true
mortal computer would be this is what
makes it artificially sentient too right
and it it has to live in its Niche and
the niche you know can get very complex
it's not going to be a laboratory that I
put it in a little uh whitew room and
you know oh okay I've emulated life no
ultimately you would want this to
integrate with human society and to
interact with us because there's things
that you get that with a group with a
colle itive with social norms that you
don't get living in pure isolation and
so you're going to get that it's not
interpretability but it's explainability
and I think that that communication and
that part might counterbalance the fact
that we're dealing with as you rightly
point out blue an extremely nonlinear
complex system that it's gonna be very
hard to say exactly why did it do what
it did based on inspection of its
contents even if we designed it so the
explainable part I think will
counterbalance that to some
degree wow sounds like Psychotherapy
Psychotherapy for the Mortal computer
there you go yes we need
it there's so many pieces to add
in I barely know where to
go yeah it's a it's a it's a lot you
brought out I think the connection to
complexity science is very good because
that's where we can ask and have a
laboratory for like well what's the
account you can give of this double
pendulum what's the account you can give
of wolfram's rule 30 what's and and by
that we can contextualize yeah how how
many experiments of what type would we
expect before we could understand a
fruit flies decision in a tze what about
a human in this or that and then this
tension but fundamental so we can
quickly come to adapt to it that there's
things we do and don't know about it's
one of the quotes beginning a chapter in
the 2022 textbook I think it's like a
Minsky quote we're aware of least what
are brains do best and so that whole
like searching under the street light
with a light of
attention that every agent is only
engaged in as a fundamental constraint
that's one constraint is the attentional
informational another constraint is the
material physical Niche which is always
actual and
that's that's um connected to the
environment totally fundamentally like
there can't be a discussion of what ant
colony foraging strategy works best even
for one field location there's going to
be different ant species with different
total strategies and different nestmates
with sub strategies as modeled by
so you've embarked on a wildly
fundamental task that combines a lot of
the discussions happening in active
inference with the broader cognitive
Sciences broader complex
systems and it's
definitely interesting and relevant so I
really appreciate that you share it this
way now happy you guys uh took to it so
well and uh I certainly want that idea
out there so now now that there's a what
do you call it a a proper treatment an
initial treatment of mortal
computation please spread the word you
know I want I want to hear other people
come back to me like oh yeah I heard
about the Mortal computer and I'd love
to see you guys and everyone else try to
take a whack at designing even the most
PR versions of it because I think this
is like I don't know if it's quite that
but it almost feels like uh like a
little baby step because if this paper
is uh is uh intensive as it has been uh
and informative and so fun working with
Carl on it um it is just a step in a big
direction as you just said Daniel and
it's a wild wild place and it also goes
at odds with a lot of like maybe this
group here you know we're a lot more
what do you say receptive and excited by
these prospects but it does go even to
challenge a lot of what we hold dear and
near and dear to ourselves which is the
we really do like our Immortal computers
and you know there there's there's going
to be tradeoffs to that and the paper
does talk about that it even starts by
trying to address the reader by saying
the reader might ask you know themselves
you know why do I really want this
because it's also very brittle I'm gonna
just be clear too but then again humans
and animals and organisms are also
brittle as well um but why do I want
this right and you know and then we had
we motivate this with like a three kind
of stabs which is thermodynamic which is
the most important and by the way the
free energy principle um in physicists
in the room might say well wait a minute
free energy that's thermodynamic why
this is not quite the same thing there's
the mixture of information theory in
here as well but you know the
thermodynamic free energy is a really
important piece to this puzzle and the
the way that computers are organized is
sort of what this challenge is and you
know it also we have tools to attack
this like neuromorphic chips wonderful
wonderful platform uh for uh you know a
mortal computer uh and we do talk about
it in the supplement it got moved to the
supplement because again I was already a
little bit too long um so I talk about
neuromorphic architectures and the also
neuromimetic algorithms which kind of
connect to the papers too like
predictive coding it isn't like front
and center I don't we don't try to like
throw it in your face uh even though it
is a a one way of thinking a a
consequence of free energy minimization
but um and so we talk about these things
but I think it challenge we also talk it
also challenges and gets us to think
about existentialism
uh and life and philosophy of life and
death because we there was even
citations to haiger uh and uh and all
kind saurin and all all kinds of
wonderful thinkers too that have just
thought about philosophy of mind and how
uh our identities and our our thought
processes are just naturally influenced
by the fact that we know uh that you
know things are going to possibly end um
and wonderful thinkers and there's also
been this concept of like again this is
a little hiigaran but uh you know your
your being there's this famous book
being in time and you think about well
you know at the end of time you you have
to understand when you live you're
projecting your being to there and then
going backwards and so there's a quote
that kind of starts the paper from sarin
kard about uh you know we we look at
life backwards but we must live it
forwards and there's that interaction
with knowing that this this Rodeo is
this play is not going to last forever
um which is a motivator for why we do a
lot of things including teaching and
passing on uh to the Next Generation and
the other part was again cognitive
science I think cognitive science got a
little bit of a spotlight uh because it
needed to I think the embodiment thesis
inactive cognition and then kofs and and
and and his Ro and his collaborators
life mind continuity thesis needed to
sort of be foregrounded a little bit um
because I think that's another piece of
this puzzle uh and it kind of ties
everything together about how to think
about minds and brains but it all
challenges what things we're we're very
used to we're very used to when we
design especially artificial
intelligence okay I I trust this
Hardware is good I'm going to try to
build some software and I believe that I
can design all my processes uh from you
know from scratch without even
accounting for maybe what you know
Evolution might have given us uh we are
seeing some of that especially basian uh
framings have some of that in there
right the idea of a prior uh I think is
important but a lot of modern-day neural
systems don't 100% I think foreground
that uh and play how important these
priors are to sort of like driving your
behavior and so that's what's kind of be
interesting is that this is truly a
weird place to be and it also really
says you got to have a body you got to
have an environment so you're not done
if you say I have this wonderful
algorithm that I think emulates some
piece of intelligence that's wonderful
but that's not going to be the end of
the story in fact you're far from the
end of the story you need to be
integrating that into a brittle body
where that process that you've designed
is also going to be shaped now by the
substrate right and its interactions its
thermodynamic exchange with the
environment the environment itself is
going to change how it works and so you
sort of get this malleable flexible kind
of framing of AI as well that
intelligence is you just no longer can
divorce it from the mechanics of
interaction with interacting with the
world you cannot divorce it from the
thermodynamic exchange that's how we're
going to get energy efficient AI I think
that's like the the other main message
but it's challenging right and others
will say well I have Quantum Computing
and it is very promising it's not any
dismissal of it um I just going to do
the same AI I've always done but faster
and do I really need to look at you know
how life emerges do I really need to
look at how neurons really do things um
you know it'll be interesting if nothing
else there might be a little bit of a
race going forward maybe it'll be the
Mortal Computing still you know on its
pedestal being the dominant Paradigm and
Mortal Computing being rather Niche for
a while I mean it's kind of same thing
with the free energy principle and
active inference I like to think of the
Mortal computation as you know another a
big expansion of free energy and active
inference because you know active
inference is a core lar of the free
energy principle and at its mortal
computer's heart is the free energy
principle right it talks about the
non-equilibrium steady state the Ness
and that's kind of like at the core and
we cast there's the other parts of the
paper there's a lot of parts of the
paper about uh inference learning and
structure and you cannot ignore any of
those pieces if you're going to build a
proper and that's actually part of our
definition there's an entanglement there
that's a whole another conversation but
um it know it's like an expansion of the
free energy principle it says you know
well what would where does this go next
and it's really like how free energy
often is used in the literature to
explain other phenomenon in like for
example Carl and many others try to use
that to do things in neuroscience and
neurophysiology and computational
Psychiatry this is what would happen if
you take the free energy principle and
you merge it with Hardware
considerations and morphology and place
it in the world of AI and you know say
what if our goal is for in silico
artificial sentience not sentients
artificial sentience and our artifacts
well this is where it's like natural
consequence so i' like to think of as
like an extension and like placing a
pathway if you come from that line of
thinking so all of you guys the active
inference institutes like perfect
candidates right because you're you're
studying deeply the free energy
principle um sting mortal computation is
just like the next step right it's like
okay well that's another piece to this
puzzle it's where you go if you want to
build technological artifacts with what
we would consider
sentients if that makes
sense
blue want to add
anything sure um I mean I I I have
millions of questions but um nothing
pressing but this one I think maybe goes
back to um you talking about cognitive
diversity and then Daniel mentioning
like shining the light of attention um
and just as we're as we're thinking
about um
like attention as as maybe like the
foundation for cognitive diversity
because like while we are all
fundamentally have the same programming
the same like voluntary and involuntary
Consciousness right I guess we'll say it
like that like my heartbeat and kind of
the my self sustaining system um we can
kind of make that conscious like I've
mentioned the breathing but also like
just through like motor control like you
can activate motor circuits like we all
have different different like some
people can spread their toes out and
some people cannot like if you've never
tried to do that like it's hard and you
have to like practice practice practice
but then like through constantly paying
attention to those like neural
connections neuromuscular connections
you you gain like a different
perspective um than others and so just
um in terms of cognitive
diversity for humans it is going to look
really different like within like in
species and inter species diversity um
is going to be crazy right like you know
a tardigrade doesn't even have a toe to
spread maybe they do I don't know
um I don't think they have toes but but
um just across the different species
maybe we this is the time to kind of
look a little closer at like procedural
memory long-term memory like at what
like what is long-term memory right like
I if um you know when you're looking at
something like an insect that doesn't
really have a brain definitely doesn't
have like a hippocampus to store the
long-term memory do you get um long-term
memory does it go into the generative
model like or where does it go like I
mean you think about they just have like
the working buffer memory or if you were
to try to design one of these cognitive
kernels for a
non-human um like maybe you don't have
to go to a plant but like where would
you start to kind of add or subtract
things like long-term memory because we
know that that's really different just
even in the animal
kingdom well
I first of all I agreed with most of
what you were saying at the beginning
and that that just resonated with
cognitive diversity um if uh talking
about like how would I design like or
begin to think about something like a
fruit fly as opposed to you know a
human again the moral computation
definition and like the general Framing
and let's just again for the audience
members that might join in and say wait
Wen what are they talking about that's
not in any of the four papers we
mentioning let's just think of the
Mortal computation thesis as subsuming
all of these because I think of all
those just as a quick point to all of
that work I think is in service of this
uh even though this was written far more
recently and I know blue you were going
to ask at one time what was the history
of the ordering of these papers but um
obviously they're not in a a strict
sequence um so it's like moral
computation is like one way to do a
synthesis of all these ideas um now to
build like something like a fruit fly
mortal computation just says you need at
least at its heart a generative model
right everything's a generative model
but the form of that generative model is
not con you know it's not specified um
because there's the the principles like
for example in that paper brings up the
cybernetic ideas of like the good
regulator theorem I'm sure you guys have
encountered this too because you kind of
ARL especially in any discussion with
those with free energy they always
borrow from cybernetics it's impossible
so law of requisite variety and the good
regulator theem are like kind of like
the most wellknown that paper talks
about a lot of other ones that I don't
think get enough attention so all the
axioms of cybernetics are kind of in
that paper but uh the good regulator
theorem and the principle of model
internal control which is not as popular
as good regulator but you sort of need
those at the formation of any of these
entities and so as long as you're able
to design the body of that fly and you
are I'm assuming you're going to study
the object in reality right so you're
going to study the actual fruit fly and
hopefully extract principles because
again this is
biomimetic so the title of the paper
says we are mimicking or performing
mimicry of biology or the things that we
perceive in our real world the
physiological
organisms and so if you're able to study
the fruit fly I would imagine you're
constructing a body that's very similar
to it tries to adhere to as many of its
physics and physical principles that
govern how it moves and interacts and
its exchange with materials you have all
that part I think you're almost there
believe it or not that's the kind of the
fun part of the mortal computer is
designing that Markov blanket implicitly
explicitly however you want to go about
it and placing in a niche gets you
really close because again embodiment
offloads a lot of that cognition because
that fruit fly does a lot of what it
does based on reactions and uh its U
interactions with its Niche and that is
where in like the 5e cognitive theory of
the paper uh the bottom the most let's
say you need this because you it
influences everything else is called
well Carl and I did introduces the it's
a rewrapping of Basil cognition you need
Elementary cognition which you could
just if you want to call it basil
cognition that's also fine we cite the
heck out of that uh in Michael Levan's
group and many other biologists so you
would be implementing that level so
you'd say if I'm going to build the
fruit fly I'm not going to be building
you know uh you know embod well you're
going to get embodied cognition from
that but you're not going to be building
these complex processes you're going to
focus on that slice that's what's kind
of nice about 5 the is you can slice it
up and say I'm going to design at this
level um obviously it the bottom level
affects the upper level so you sort of
do have to account for that and so you
would be saying well what are the basil
cognitive functions that Define
something like a fruit fly what does it
do what would evolution of given it
because if you're not going to simulate
Evolution which would give you those
things if you know properly done and
with enough compute uh you're going to
design those inductive biases you're
going to hopefully study the fruit fly
and then its internal cognitive model
will not be the common model of
cognition because the common model of
cognition is sort of like okay that was
the product of the human evolutionary
track right and that's what evolution
gave us is like our organizing principle
of the brain but other animals don't
necessarily have that to the same degree
and creatures as you get smaller and
smaller and simp let's say different on
the Spectrum especially as you move
towards things that are a little bit
simpler like single cell organisms
they're going to have a lot less of that
functionality but still under the hood
is that generative model it just might
not be a generative model as in like oh
I have a neural circuit that's trying to
predict the next uh state of the
environment like a fantasy or a dream
sequence that I unroll out like we
humans can sort of like oh let me think
about what's going to happen if I close
my eyes and I knock over the computer we
can use our internal physics simulation
to figure out what it's going to do and
say nah I'm not gonna do that whereas a
flute fly might have some sense of
physics but it might not be like Oh I'm
rolling out over long-term trajectory so
I'm not going to be building for example
um a procedural memory or an episodic
memory quite like what I do in the
common model of cognition and I might
only need very simple little neural
circuits because again the number of
neurons and for example like insects is
really really really small and that's
why we can study them better too that's
also why people study that or even like
it's not necessarily the same as a fruit
flights it's a lot simpler but still
fascinating is C Elegance right has been
studied a lot because we can map out
every single bit of its neural circuits
and that and of itself is rather complex
so I would argue that the fruit fly
cognitive model will be simpler will and
it will be dictated by what we decide
are the elementary cognitive functions
uh that make its mortal computer it a
mortal computer and we won't need you
know these complex moduls uh interacting
in the way we do uh in for example you
know a human model or let's say an
animal model um I think the that's but
again that's grounded in something like
you understand you're mimicking so if
you go with the route of biomimicry you
should probably be studying the fruit
fly or at least understand what we
understand about it and dissect that and
bring back what are its base functions
and then how am I emulating that and
then you know you build your little
cognitive internal States right inside
the Marco blanket that maintain for
example what are the V essential
variables that the fruit fly needs to
maintain it's not going to be the same
biochemical processes that dictate a
human right like for example when we
have blood we're looking at like pH
level and temperature the fruit fly
might be looking at a little bit
different essential variables right
certain con chemical concentrations
matter to it more um you'd want to model
that and I think that that by the way
when you talk about the basil cognition
in designing it my my thought on this is
that you are approaching it from what
are those life sustaining variables that
characterize that start from there and
then you say okay well does
explain some of the things that I
observe you know let's say again we're
modeling at this point but you know what
the fruit fly does like for example
flying around why does it fly around
well maybe it's because it needs to you
know reach this particular nutrient and
so it knows if I go to this region I am
more likely to achieve it that might be
an allostatic process right and You' say
okay there's something that I need uh
and this could also be like a bottomup
design right if you don't think that you
need like the inductive bias that's
provided by the common model you sort of
build your little functions as needed
and now you build your little internal
generative model your good regulator
right into the fruit fly based on the
key functions it needs to satisfy so
that it does not die right um and
ultimately the best way to probably do
this is then you simulate Evolution
right and maybe you let some natural
selection happen because if you don't
want to design those processes then
you'd want to simulate you know the
origins of it and by the way mortal
computation doesn't ignore Evolution
here it doesn't talk about designing it
because you know that's a whole realm in
of itself but even the life mind
continuity thesis from kof's group uh
they talk about you need a selection
history and I think the only way to get
around the selection history is and you
say well okay if I'm not going to
simulate the selection history and let
you know these Primitives emerge into
the structures that make for example
fruit fly work you need to figure out
well what was those what was the product
of our current n selection history right
what did Evolution do to give the fruit
fly as is so it's you got like two
choices study the real thing and try to
emulate some of those very basic
principles like identifying its
essential variables identifying
allostatic processes that might service
those essential variables in the
homostasis of them or the hormesis of
them um or talk about some very basic
Primitives and then say I'm going to
simulate a population of these and that
might be more difficult because if
you're dealing with the actual like
let's say you have a little fruit fly
robot since we're talking about
substrates that might be not very cheap
to do where it might be easier to do it
in simulation and doing it with a
digital morphology and that's another
can of warms so I don't know if that
kind of gives
you something blue no it definitely does
um and like yeah so sorry my my brain
works faster than my tongue sometimes
insects definitely have brains just
nothing like our brains they just
definitely don't have brains like ours
right like so nothing that we can map
analogously over um although some of the
neurotransmitters and things still work
but just in a different functional way
to my to my knowledge um also Andrew
Baron is building like a tremendous
model of the honeybee brain that is just
so super cool I think if you don't know
his work it's really really NE send me a
link to that I'd love to see that that
sounds awesome yeah it's way cool um has
them running around in mazes and doing
all kinds of learning like how to tell a
van go apart from a Monae I mean they're
they're really doing some pretty pretty
complex uh stuff and and and that's why
like it's um you know always makes me
wonder like where does this stuff go
like like where does where is the memory
there um and and it's just it's such a
fascinating process to me um how
memories are created and stored and like
how they map into the brain and like
sometimes I can pull something up right
away and like sometimes it'll take me
four days to remember someone's name
like what was the name of and like I'll
remember it I'll be just driving down
the road it was whatever and like it's
just like how many layers of circuitry
did I have to like transgress to get
from A to B you know um and like yeah
how how do different kinds of animals do
that is always really fascinating to me
I think a piece of that too is evolution
also has a memory right right and I
think that selection history is what
goes into things like for example the
fruit fly right so there's its
predecessors you know you know maybe
they did certain other behaviors that
were not in conducive to their survival
I think there's that too that implicit
kind of memory and then that gets
encoded uh in the morphology right and
this is where it goes back to where I
just said if you want it or like your
your collaborator your friend that you
mentioned about designing like the
honeybees uh it's kind of the same
principles you say well okay what did
Evolution give it let me design that
you're just skipping the evolutionary
phase and I think there's some memory in
the structure too so this is where the
body now of course your example about
you retrieving it there's layers of
intricacy there like I'm not cleaning
about that but even like the fruit fly
why does it remember to do certain
things or why does it seem to have
certain patterns and that's also what
the moral computation thesis does in
account for or at least tries to by
saying that it is because that body
changes and it's you know subject to a
selection history because it's
constantly in this eternal change of
repair and maintenance in the face of
disintegration because it's always the
threat of disintegration uh your your
your identity will cease when you die um
and so because of that things get
encoded in that memory and that's also
this beautiful piece of like the
interplay of physics and cybernetics um
this is without ever getting into the
probably wonderful Quantum
interpretations I'm sure Chris Fields
could Enlighten us all about um but you
know the idea that information or
variety gets encoded into these intera
through its interactions gets encoded
into the morphology the very
organization and structural
manifestation of that organization
because organization is not structure it
is the relationships of the parts and it
can exist independent of the
manifestation and the manif station is
like oh okay here's the body that
embodies those principles that also
encodes that is a memory because for
example uh an organism that understands
a particular chemical interaction might
say well look I need to filter out this
toxin or I'm gonna die and I need pump
in these nutrients that's a memory it's
just not a retrievable memory it's just
like an implicit memory um but that's
why for example it's able to conduct the
actions that it does and this is why
mortal computation really tries to and
this is where I think it's very forward
thinking or very far ahead of what we
can probably even do easily which is it
really says you do need to understand
the body the substrate is so important
and understanding how that will then
affect the internal States and how you
do this processing that has to be at the
front and center of your story of
whatever you build um and then the niche
you can't escape the niche
you're you're kind of by having a body
you're like well okay but the body only
existed because it was in response to
the environment and it was you know it
has evolved or it has adapted because of
the pertubations the environment has
subjected it to um and so I think that
that's what that's why I like the thesis
so much is it's kind of say we need to
flip our thinking a bit not okay we're
going to design the brain and someday in
the future we'll have good bodies for it
I think that that was valuable and it
has produced some interesting things but
it can only get you so far and then you
miss at least 50% of the puzzle that
could also inform that design where we
talked earlier about like emotions and
you know I don't I wouldn't argue that
the systems that we have today despite
the media claims and you know there's
the stuff with open Ai and I saw some
comments about oh well you know Alton
and others they they have some secret
AGI program but I've heard conspiracies
about that stuff all the time so I I
don't I put too much Credence to it um I
don't think that they've cracked the the
emotional nut the biophysical nut I
think it's more like a we've had lots of
people either argue study very specific
slices of it um but those voices need to
be echoed right and so that's what I
think the moral computation is an echo
as well
of at least like a century of thought
uh and it's saying this is how we can
approach artificial general intelligence
and then it can account for things like
the fruit fly actually your uh the the
you said Andrew was his name on the work
on like Honeys that to me is an example
of if you know he's got a learning
component and an influential component
and there is some organiz he has a body
he has a niche you know that that's very
close to an in silico version of a
mortal computer right I you know the
only other components that it might be
more like an allostatic MC so and again
in the paper we have a table uh and Carl
did want that to stay I was going to
move it to the appendix again length um
so we made a compressed table of
different types of uh moral computers
and we kind of characterize them there's
a few that are autopedic we actually do
have very like uh
organoids really really close to what
you would want right but they're all
biophysical so there's not like a oh I
designed something on a neuromorphic
chip with predictive coding like what I
would do um this is you know oh we're
using stem cells to construct this
microphysiological architectures I do
think that has a placed a super
important role going forward and I would
only hope that there's some
democratization of an exchange of ideas
between this wonderful really new world
in machine intelligence um to learn and
study organoids uh but also fungal and
mold-based Computing really interesting
place to be as well um and to think
about how does that biophysical
organization give rise to commun and
those are examples of mortal computers
um uh ashp's homeostat deserves a lot of
love and attention because it's the
oldest and really the most prominent
example of what I would argu is a true
in silico uh mortal computer but it's
homeostatic little bit alost static
depending on what you've done there's
variations to it um but like the
xenobots really interesting uh I think
the xenobots are an example of something
that they use frog cells leg cells and
pieces of frogs to actually instantiate
these little tiny robots that can
self-heal and repair and I think that's
going to be the part where we have
autopedic computers already in front of
us like organoids and xenobots are some
of the most interesting I think profound
examples of how you get this computer
and then for example Andrew's work would
have you know maybe the missing
component so his would be more
allostatic so mid-level kind of mortal
computers and I'd have to read more
about them but just from your exp
explanation um but the structural
selection the evolution of the
morphology the self-replication part of
the story which we also talk about as
well um is more in like the xenobots and
so I think it's interesting how do those
two worlds interact and how do you get
those properties of
self-repair self uh replication which by
the way if you add a mutation to
self-replication you get reproduction
because now that creates a new system
that's now subject to Natural Selection
and now you've you know essentially done
reproduction and now we have an account
you your your your computer has all the
pieces that you know complex organisms
do to also ensure their persistence
which is we have Offspring right you
know that's another way we project
ourselves into the future uh in an
indirect way so it'd be kind of cool to
take like the honeybee model and think
about what are the ways in which we can
have its morphology be damaged and
conduct self-repair and that gets into
the real nitty-gritty and even it might
be difficult to do right and that's
where I think the this is where the
Grand Challenge right it's got an open
an open pathway that I don't think like
any one of us has an exact candidate you
know for okay there's it already exists
because there'd be really no point in
writing the paper um I do think the
xenobots and organoids can teach us a
tremendous amount about structural
selection Mor
morphogenesis uh and self-repair and
then maybe May build like a you know a a
synthetic uh you know honeybee mortal
computer that also is autoptic right
it's able to constantly uh repair itself
to some degree I mean that that would be
very interesting so the fact that you
brought that up was kind of like oh
that's that's probably another example
of a in silico Mortal computer versus a
biophysical we have we have some good
examples of biophysical not as many in
silico to my knowledge even like robots
today they're not mortal right they
there might be some interesting things
I'm not aware of but uh largely they're
like they have all the part s they have
the ingredients I think for uh mortal
computers but they're not they're not
completely there yet and so I think that
making a robot inherently whatever the
robot system it could be the honeybee it
could be an a creature that we come up
with it could be humanoid um making it
inherently driven by just this
fundamental process of persistence is
the starting point and then thinking
about what are those essential variables
and like we talked about the fruit fly
designing all of those principles from
the ground up and then at one point you
got to say is this supposed to be human
likee uh am i g to be able to evolve you
know a population of these or am I going
to need to employ uh inductive biases
like a common model of cognition and I
like to think of Co cognitive
architectures as a possible bias and say
well okay I'm going to design a brain
based on these principles it could be
the wrong bias but you know what we it's
probably capturing a lot in you know
cognitive architectures are fit to a lot
of human data so they do explain a lot
of different effects so I I would say
it's a pretty good bet um and you bring
in those biases and now you design the
internal States and now you have a a
very complicated mortal computer but you
know the future will be a very
interesting place and hopefully uh more
interesting mortal computers will emerge
in the
future
thank you Alex these are really great
points in
closing blue first as as much as you'd
like to add and then Alex any closing
thoughts that you want to kind of leave
it
with um just I don't know that Andrew
Baron is building a robot B that would
be super cool um he's just modeling the
real actual biological honey be brain
which does some level of mortal
Computing I guess it is a mortal
computer right like the the but it's not
it's in Vivo not in solico um but Alex
thank you so much for um entertaining
all of my fun questions and for you know
transing us down this like super fun
path toward mortal Computing I'm super
excited to read your new paper um and
appreciate your time on the
stream yeah thank you uh thank you blue
and thank you Daniel for inviting me
this was a really thrilling discussion I
really like your your guys podcast
series and uh and I think it's it's
great that you guys are pushing for The
Narrative of free energy and active
inference and trying to educate the the
greater public on it so my students as I
already told you are fans of your
channel so it was H it was my pleasure
to be on here um I hope you guys enjoy
the paper um and I guess as a one final
comment I guess it's now sort of Our Own
Private running joke uh again for those
that tuned in hoping to like have a deep
time into I think you guys did a good
job on point zero going through all four
of those papers to be fair I think that
captured their Essence and then last
time at the end of 0.1 I gave like a
crash course on the NGC predictive
coding um so just to make a final
comment to sort of like tie everything
together to today's I didn't actually
expect I it's my fault for introducing
the paper but it may it was a welcome uh
derailment uh going down mortal computer
but I think those four papers um you
could argue are like building blocks as
well there are other pieces to the
puzzle of mortal computation for example
my my preference or my thoughts are
predictive coding which is a
manifestation of free energy or
variational free energy
minimization that's going to be an
important important piece your neural
circuitry should probably adhere to that
because I think it's very friendly to a
lot of Hardware like neuromorphic chips
so that's kind of like where all the
predictive coding stuff just to think
about my papers there you're like oh
okay that's how that relates it's
probably going to be the allostatic
processes if I were to guess uh and
building circuits there and building
little modules like we do in COG engine
uh the Cog engine paper is we have
talked about it even if it's not about
it specifically the common model of
cognition
is a wonderful bias if you want to try
to skip ahead rather than evolve from
the ground up to human cognition um and
if we want to build a mortal computer
that has aspects of human behavior we
should maybe appeal to that type of bias
um there's a lot more in the world and I
encourage you know viewers to go into
the world of cognitive science and
computational Neuroscience and dig into
the Eternal well that is of the
knowledge there um so I recommend that
and that's how that paper relates the
spiking predictive coding and the
convolutional which we didn't we only
like sort of like touched on them
briefly I'll just comment that the
convolutional predictive coding paper
which was like the second one that you
guys talked about is like an extension
of the nature paper NGC and it just says
how do we do Vision processing I
consider that as another version of the
same building block that would go into a
mortal computer and the spiking
predictive coding I think is really
interesting it says well if I'm going to
try to get as close as I can to
biophysical right and get as close as I
can to neuromorphics we should be able
to think about what do real neurons do
so it's kind of like we're building the
neuron as a little biome uh little
mortal computer and of itself and we
know that they communicate with spikes
um and so the spiking predictive coding
is like uh one way there's other ways uh
to emulate predictive coding at a very
fine course fine grained Dynamics level
and I would imagine that that would
probably be a great way to build a
neuromorphic chip based mortal computer
so the idea is if you get into
neuromorphics and the Mortal Computing
paper does talk talk about it not in
great detail um it talks about even my
other work uh that's beyond predictive
coding like Ford forward predictive Ford
forward only learning and other variants
um and also Spike timing dependent
plasticity and how did all those relate
to the Mortal computer and I that's in a
supplement so if you're like really a
glutton for punishment and you can't get
enough there's you know an appendix of a
couple sections um and it's talked about
there and so I think that you can just
for the viewers of this podcast this
closing podcast it could be like well
that's how it all relates really it was
all parts of a mortal computer and we
can all pretend that from the beginning
I had envisioned a mortal computer even
though that only came out uh the
framework in the last months I see all
those parts as giving rise to that and
there are tools that you can use just
like Daniel brought up the whole like
framework of active inference and the
free energy principle and B asianism uh
they're all tools that might help you
build you know very powerful and
interesting mortal computers whether
they are simulated or whether they're
real world um and then as we brought up
in this one you guys have and I think
it's a compliment to like some of Chris
Field's teachings and some of his work
there's the also the whole Quantum
interpretation not Quantum Computing as
a solution but rather oh mortal computer
and a neuromorphic system which That's
What You Know Carl and Chris did and
Carl and I did in Mortal computation the
interpretation from the quantum
information theoretic could be a very
promising uh way of formulating it and
right and that might open up the doors
to an extremely powerful form like in
Quantum Computing so I think there's a
lot of wonderful wild out there places
to go but they're not too out there
that's my last point that I want to make
they're they're out there they go
against a lot of our like I said earlier
held beliefs especially those tied to
Immortal computation but I also think
that there's they kind of build on
intuitions and ideas that have existed
in other places like if we take biology
and biochemistry and biophysics
seriously um and we know that these
things work so it's not like oh I'm
going to uh do something drastically
strange and controversial it's just
saying let's take a little bit deeper
inspiration from the world around us and
living entities to build what could
arguably be one way to do artificial
general intelligence and ultimately
artificial sentience which I think is
kind of like the the final end goal
right and then yeah and we end up there
so thank you guys again it was so much
fun talking letting thank you for
letting me at some points ramble I hope
my rambling was useful but you
know thank you I'll give a short closing
remark so first thank you blue for
working on the dot zero diligently and
thank you Alex for like suggesting to
take on this Challenge and reading
between and among the citations is like
always what it's about and the
engagement and the developments in the
real world so it's it's just epic it's
fun and it's live the research program
is lived forward but experienced
backwards or however it was um
definitely very excited for everything
you've described and on on all these
topics I I hope we can continue to
discuss and that people will be excited
to step up and do like a
56.3 um and we can just like continue
working together and I'll close actually
just by reading a short selection from
an abstract because I think it really
contextualizes a a big um element of
basian mechanics so this is the paper is
there a Newton of the blade of grass by
Peter Schuster 2011 so just the first
sentences in 1790 Emanuel Kant makes the
famous statement in his critique of
judgment there will never be a Newton of
the blade of grass because human science
will never be able to explain how a
living being can originate from
inanimate matter the German naturalist
Ernst heel about 70 years later
celebrates Charles Darwin to be such a
Newton of the grass blate hegel's
enthusiasm about Darwin was not shared
among his contemporaries and is not too
widespread today although the
pathbreaking role of Darwin's scholarly
work is not the least doubted or
questioned the American philosopher
physicist and molecular biologist Evelyn
Fox Keller says that considering Darwin
as the Newton of biology is simply wrong
Darwin himself has systematically
avoided dwelling upon the question of
how life has originated from inanimate
materials natural selection begins with
a living
cell and I think it's actually this
Nexus
that you're addressing with the 1900s
and early 2000s in mind that is a big
one so thank you again for for
undertaking the project and for joining
the streams and talk to you next time
yeah thank you for having me again
looking forward to the next time bye
byeone
I